A Guide to the James J. Kilpatrick Papers ca. 1967-1993
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The James J. Kilpatrick Papers ca. 1967-1993
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6626-r
ca. 2,000 items (5 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2 linear feet)
This addition to the Papers of James J. Kilpatrick consist of published books, correspondence, topical files, manuscripts and contract for articles, forewords, and speeches, ca. 1967- 1993.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by James J. Kilpatrick, Charleston, South Carolina, on September 20, 1995.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of American columnist James J. Kilpatrick, ca. 1967-1993, consists of his published books, A Political Bestiary with Eugene J. McCarthy and illustrated by Jeff MacNelly (1978), A Bestiary of Bridge(1986, also an Italian edition), and The Ear is Human, all signed by the author, and The American South Four Seasons of the Land with photographs by William A. Bake (1980, unsigned); correspondence; topical files; manuscripts and contracts for articles, forewords, and speeches; and the original manuscripts and notes for Fine Print, Reflections on the Writing Art(1993).
Correspondents include Shana Alexander, Dr. Stephen Barrett, Hamilton Productions, Inc., and John Logue. Topical correspondence includes the Rappahannock High School Literary Fund, Sixty Minutes, the Virginia Commission Bicentennial of the United States Constitution, Universal Press Syndicate, and the U.S. News and World Report error concerning the number of speeches given by Kilpatrick per year.
The papers also contain commencement addresses, speeches and articles for National Review, Nation's Business, The Richmond Times-Dispatch, Southern Living, Washington Journalism Review, and The Washingtonian. Topics of his articles and speeches include current events and issues, the Constitution, Barry Goldwater, Patrick Henry, federalism, civil rights, civil liberties, and copy editing.
Organization
The collection is arranged in two series: Correspondence and Topical Files; and Manuscripts of Articles, Books and Speeches.
Contents List
- Correspondence & Topical Files
  - Alexander, Shana 1974-1990 (Box 1)
  - Barrett, Dr. Stephen re Laetrile Controversy 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Contracts 1976-1980 (Box 1)
  - Logue, John re The American South Four Seasons of the Land 1979-1982 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1972-1992 (Box 1)
  - Rappahannock High School Literary Fund 1984-1990 (Box 1)
  - Sixty Minutes 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - U.S. News and World Report"Boner" re the Number of Kilpatrick Speeches per Year 1982 (Box 1)
  - Universal Press Syndicate 1979-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Virginia Commission Bicentennial of the United State Constitution 1982-1990 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts of Articles, Books & Speeches
  - Books
    - The American South Four Seasons of the Land 1880, Galley Proofs (Box 2)
    - Fine Print, Reflections on the Writing Art 1991-1992, Notes (7 folders) (Box 2)
    - Fine Print, Reflections of the Writing Art 1992, Typed Manuscript (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Fine Print, Reflections on the Writing Art 1992, Typed Manuscript with editorial corrections (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Fine Print, Reflections on the Writing Art 1993, Typed Manuscript with corrections by the author (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - Fine Print, Reflections on the Writing Art 1993, Page Proofs, pages 1-196 (Box 4)
    - Fine Print, Reflections on the Writing Art 1993, Index (Box 4)
  - Articles & Speeches
    - The American Legion Article "The Constitution is what the Judges Say it is" 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Arizona Republic Article re Barry Goldwater 1986 (Box 4)
    - Daughters of the American Revolution Speech "The Prophetic Mr. Henry" 1980 (Box 4)
    - International Platform Association Presentation to Reed Larson 1980 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Artilces (Pending) 1987-1990 (Box 5)
    - National Review Articles 1985 (Box 5)
    - National Town Meeting Speech "Whatever Happened to Dreams and Heroes?" 1980 (Box 5)
    - Nation's Business Articles 1978-1987, 8 folders (Box 5)
    - North Carolina State University Lecture "Federalism and Civil Rights" 1967 (Box 5)
    - Pennsylvania Society Speech 1981 (Box 5)
    - Randolph-Macon Academy, Front Royal, Virginia, Commencement Address 1981 (Box 5)
    - Ravenscroft School, Raleigh, North Carolina, Commencement Address 1980 (Box 5)
    - Richmond Times-Dispatch Articles 1988-1989 (Box 5)
    - Southern Living Article re the Jefferson Memorial 1988-1989 (Box 5)
    - Sovran Annual Report Article re "The Crescent" 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - Tennessee Bar Association Speech 1978 (Box 5)
    - Trooper Down by Marie Bartlett (book not present), Foreword by James J. Kilpatrick [1988] (Box 5)
    - University of Tennessee, College of Law Speech 1974 (Box 5)
    - Untitled Article re the Mood of the Country [1985] (Box 5)
    - Washington Journalism Review Article "Doesn't Anyone Edit Copy Anymore?" 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - The Washingtonian Article "Notes on Virginia" 1984 (Box 5)